<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>A storytelling project about memory, identity, and family.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 16:17:58 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 16:17:58 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Aunt Mary and the Burgess Boardinghouse</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I found myself in Towson, Maryland, with a couple of hours to kill and a family story to pursue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My great-aunt Mary–my grandfather’s oldest sister–was a genealogy enthusiast and, until her death, the resident expert on the Newman family. Years later, I happened across a Newman family tree she made in 1987, annotated in her distinctive handwriting with family stories. One of these stories was about Aunt Maggie Burgess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maggie was Jacob Newman’s sister and aunt to the Newman aunts. She married William Burgess, a Civil War veteran and railroad agent; they had five daughters and lived in southern Pennsylvania. Later, the then-widowed Maggie moved to Towson, Maryland, with her daughters, where, in the 1920s, they “kept a boardinghouse in a large, porticoed white house with ‘grounds,’” according to Aunt Mary. “At 6 or 7 or 8 or thereabouts I went with Uncle Jake and maybe Kate or Bab on occasional trips ‘for the day’ to the Burgess household/boardinghouse in Towson (when Jake was visiting from Pittsburgh for weekends).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story makes me picture a large Victorian house full of Newman (technically, Burgess) women. Maggie, the matriarch, remembered by Aunt Mary as a “very little woman in black with a cane.” Maggie’s oldest daughter Lula Heffelfinger, who moved to Towson after being widowed, accompanied at times by her daughter Mary and her granddaughter Nancy. Lula’s younger sister, Margaret, who was unmarried. And, a favorite of her Newman cousins, the youngest, Nan, a “large, cheerful woman” (Aunt Mary’s words again), who had a career as a singer and while traveling, met and married Hobart Smock, a tenor, who also ended up at the boardinghouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I later learned, Hobart Smock was the original &lt;em&gt;owner&lt;/em&gt; of the house. According to photos at the Baltimore County Public Library (see note below), he purchased the house in 1908, a few years after his marriage to Nan, and called it “Carolcroft,” because of his interest in glee clubs and choirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many reasons, it does not surprise me that, even as he played a critical role in the Burgess boardinghouse, Hobart Smock was only a footnote in Aunt Mary’s retelling. Up against the Newman women, even an illustrious tenor would be harmonizing in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;§&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting in my rental car in Towson, I fired up Google Maps. Census records told me that the house was located on Aigburth Road, so I set out for that address, looking for large, porticoed houses that might match Aunt Mary’s description. I wasn’t sure if this quest would bear fruit–house numbers and street names probably have changed since the early 1900s–but fortunately, I also had an old photo I had stumbled across during my research, which although a bit blurry, gave me an image of a house with a gabled roof and two large chimneys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GPS announced that I had arrived at my destination, just as I pulled up in front of Towson High School, and as I looked to my right, I saw, half-hidden by trees, a large house with a front porch, looking very similar to the house depicted in the photo I had found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/towson-house.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;House in Towson, Maryland&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The railings on the front porch had been updated, and the house was both green and white, but it appeared that the Burgess boardinghouse was still standing, after more than a hundred years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t linger at the house–just long enough to take a photo and note the location for future reference–yet this short trip has remained with me. The experience of visiting places that were important to my ancestors helps me feel connected to them, in a way that transcends memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Locating and visiting historic homes is a ritual that I will always associate with Aunt Mary. My father has photographs taken during his trips with her to find our ancestors’ homes in southeastern Pennsylvania, denoted with the addresses and directions. Emboldened by my high school independent study on family history, during my senior year, I assembled these directions into an itinerary, and that summer, on the way home from–of all places–touring Goucher College in Towson, Maryland, my family visited these houses and towns where our ancestors had spent their lives. Though she was not with us, Aunt Mary was our tour guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a postcard that Aunt Mary sent my brother and me in 1997. In it, she thanks us for sending her a postcard from Gettysburg, where we had just gone on vacation. At the end, she asks, “Did you also see the town where your Dad lived when he was a boy?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/postcard.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Postcard from Aunt Mary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not just the stories we tell, but the places where we live out our lives, that should be remembered, and passed on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: The photos below of the Aigburth Road house come from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://catalog.bcpl.lib.md.us/polaris/search/searchresults.aspx?ctx=1.1033.0.0.5&amp;amp;type=Keyword&amp;amp;term=205%20Aigburth%20Road*&amp;amp;by=KW&amp;amp;sort=RELEVANCE&amp;amp;limit=TOM=dmc&amp;amp;query=&amp;amp;page=0&amp;amp;searchid=3&quot;&gt;Baltimore County Public Library collection&lt;/a&gt;. They depict a dark and ornate interior, with patterned wallpaper, dark furniture, oriental rugs, and–befitting a musical household–a piano. The photos were taken by William C. Kenney, c. 1917-1919.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/house-interior.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Interior of house&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/house-interior1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Interior of house&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/2017/10/13/aunt-mary-burgess-boardinghouse.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/2017/10/13/aunt-mary-burgess-boardinghouse.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Not Knowing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been lingering on a post about &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/babbie&quot;&gt;Babbie&lt;/a&gt; for several weeks now. I’d like to blame my delay on personal and professional travel, on taking on some freelance work, on a huge stack of books next to my bed demanding my attention. But the truth is, I’ve just had a hard time wrapping my head around this next post. I’ve been doing research, jotting down notes, and drafting prose, but it hasn’t been coming together cohesively. Today I realized that there’s a story hidden in that post, and until I tell it and reflect on what it might mean, I won’t be able to truly tell the story of Babbie’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 5, 1925, Babbie’s middle son, Richard, committed suicide by taking cyanide. He was 25 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Gettysburg Times&lt;/em&gt; reported the details. Richard “died from the effects of poison which was self administered. A note left by the young man explained why he committed the act. Despondency was given as the reason, this being brought on by ill health. The young man had been a sufferer from heart trouble for a number of years.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newspaper account relates how Richard had seemed his usual self, had eaten dinner with his parents before going upstairs to bed around 10:00 p.m. Then there is the moment that sticks with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“He was not heard moving about the house after this time, but shortly after midnight &lt;strong&gt;his mother&lt;/strong&gt; heard him moaning as though in great pain.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This grisly newspaper article depicts Babbie at a moment in time. It is the moment right before her husband Abner climbs to the attic, to discover his son’s body, with a note next to it. It is the moment right before she is greeted with intense sorrow, pain, and confusion. It is the moment right before she realizes that she has lost her son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the lone suicide in our family history. Over the course of ten years, the Newman aunts lost three men in their lives to suicide. I’ve already told of how Eve’s husband, &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve/2017/02/06/who-was-alan-gilmour&quot;&gt;Alan Gilmour&lt;/a&gt;, committed suicide, only eight months before Edward. There is also the aunts’ brother Jake, my great-great uncle, who committed suicide in 1935, by sitting in a running car inside his garage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am drawn to speculate about why these men would commit suicide. &lt;em&gt;The Gettysburg Times&lt;/em&gt; refers to longstanding heart problems for Richard. Alan Gilmour’s obituary mentions his health failing a year before his death. According to family stories, Jake was never as successful in business as his older brothers, and he was gay at a time when homosexuality was not accepted. It is easy to seek out these explanations, to accept them as truth, to codify them and make them part of the story that I am telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the only true thing is that I will never know what really happened. I will never be able to understand why they felt such desperation that they wanted to take their own lives. I will never be able to answer the many questions that surround their deaths. So, instead, I ask myself why I am so caught up by this story. Why can’t I just finish my next post about Babbie and continue on with this project?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about these tragic deaths, I think less about the men, but about the women they left behind. After so much loss–so sudden, so unexplainable–how do you move on? How do you rebuild your life after your partner leaves you? How do you recover from the death of a child? How do you feel the absence of a sibling and not experience overwhelming heartache and sorrow every day? And, finally, how do you live with the “not knowing”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always like to have an explanation. I want answers, and it’s hard when I can’t find them. My search for answers is what started me on this project, but I won’t be able to answer every question I have. When I think about Richard, Alan, and Jake, I will have to live with the “not knowing,” which echoes down through the generations, from my great-great aunts, down to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/98317926@N04/9572145584/&quot;&gt;“Shadows”&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/98317926@N04/&quot;&gt;Tomi Lattu&lt;/a&gt; is licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 2.0 License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jul 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/babbie/2017/07/04/not-knowing.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/babbie/2017/07/04/not-knowing.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Babbie</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Agnes at State College</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/agnes&quot;&gt;Agnes&lt;/a&gt; was &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/agnes/2016/09/23/agnes-forestry&quot;&gt;refused entry to the Pennsylvania State Forestry Academy&lt;/a&gt;, she didn’t give up on her ambitions for higher education. In the fall of 1917, she was one of five “farmerettes” studying agriculture at State College (now Pennsylvania State University). “Five girls with back-to-the-farm hankerings, are studying scientific farming in the two-year agricultural course at the Pennsylvania State College,” the &lt;em&gt;Indiana Gazette&lt;/em&gt; reported. Even though the United States was by then at war, the newspaper account claimed that this had “nothing to do whatever in their choice of a profession. They simply wanted to learn how to feed chickens, hoe beans, milk cows and plough. Later they expect to use their knowledge in managing their own farms.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State College’s two-year course in agriculture was, according to the 1917-18 course catalog, “designed to meet the needs of young men with farm experience who are not prepared to enter the four-year courses in agriculture.” (91) The emphasis on young men was not entirely true; in 1912, the course had been formally opened to women–albeit with modification. Students could take courses in the domestic arts, while also developing knowledge in scientific agriculture, with the ultimate goal of being able to “make a living on the farm.” “Country girls” who graduate “find on their return home that their interests are elsewhere. They have been unfitted rather than fitted for life in the country,” wrote Margaret B. MacDonald in &lt;em&gt;The Penn State Farmer&lt;/em&gt;. By allowing women to gain a more well-rounded knowledge of agriculture, “the object of the course is to make successful, resourceful, happy women of farmers’ wives and daughters.” (201)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the newspaper account and Penn State’s own publication attributed the goals of the two-year agriculture program and the women who attended it to developing the knowledge and skills to work on farms, often as wives and daughters of farmers. For someone as independent as Agnes, who had at one point aspired to the male-dominated profession of forestry, would this have been her goal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agnes’s ultimate goal may in fact have been to further her education beyond the initial two-year program, as she subsequently enrolled in the four-year course in Horticulture at Penn State. This program included courses on plant breeding, floriculture, vegetable gardening, landscape gardening, and entomology, as well as a summer practicum, consisting of “six weeks of survey work in commercial truck gardens, florists’ establishments, nurseries, orchards, greenhouses, and small fruit plantations.” (126) Classes, as described in the course catalog, included recitation and practicum hours, emphasizing the practical application of the studies the students were undertaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0px;&quot; src=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=3KRIAQAAMAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA124&amp;amp;output=embed&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;900&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from her studies, Agnes appears to have been an active student at State College. She was a member of the Press Club, Crab Apple Club, Current Events Club, and Penn State Grange, and was active in athletics. She played hockey and basketball, received class numerals for her high scoring, and even served as president of the Women’s Athletic Association during her senior year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Agnes’s more amusing activities involved serving on a committee that banned “improper dancing,” such as “cheek-to-cheek” or “toddling,” at house parties and college dances. The committee was “instructed to demonstrate before the Women’s Student Association just what is and what is not acceptable as proper form on the dance floor. This group will meet at the close of the Christmas vacation and their recommendations will be law.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Agnes graduated from State College in 1922, she became the first in the Newman family to earn a college degree. As the youngest child, she likely benefitted from changing attitudes about higher education for women. It is somewhat surprising, however, that only a few months after her graduation, Agnes married a farmer, fulfilling Penn State’s goal for her to become a “successful, resourceful, happy” farmer’s wife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agnes and her husband, Milton Lightwood, performed agricultural work at her &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/meg/2017/03/21/meg-experimental-services&quot;&gt;sister Meg’s settlement house&lt;/a&gt; and then started their own, ultimately unsuccessful, fruit farm in Maryland. Agnes’s horticultural education would continue, however, as she later attended the Ambler School of Horticulture for Women, and after her divorce from Milton in the 1940s, she finally embarked on the professional career in horticulture that she had initially prepared for during her time at State College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Works Referenced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Five Girls Study Farming.” &lt;em&gt;The Indiana Gazette&lt;/em&gt; (Indiana, Pennsylvania), 9 October 1917, p. 9.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Improper Dancing Ban.” &lt;em&gt;The Reading Times&lt;/em&gt; (Reading, Pennsylvania), 18 December 1920, p. 3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MacDonald, Margaret B. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=S8HNAAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA200&amp;amp;lpg=PA200&amp;amp;dq=penn+state+two+years+agriculture+course+women&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=yuf_OYnI54&amp;amp;sig=AGP1jhz7u5CTKBVO0k0OMPYjy0E&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwi98NvTzZfTAhWKx4MKHe1eCyUQ6AEIUDAJ#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=penn%20state%20two%20years%20agriculture%20course%20women&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;“Education of Girls for Life on the Farm.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Penn State Farmer&lt;/em&gt;, 1912, p. 200-201.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pennsylvania State College. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=nadIAQAAMAAJ&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Pennsylvania State College Bulletin: General Catalogue 1917-1918&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; State College, 1918.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pennsylvania State College. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=3KRIAQAAMAAJ&amp;amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Pennsylvania State College Bulletin: General Catalogue 1919-1920&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; State College, 1920.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;http://digicoll.library.wisc.edu/WebZ/FETCH?sessionid=01-61790-1524838938&amp;amp;recno=4&amp;amp;resultset=2&amp;amp;format=F&amp;amp;next=html/nffull.html&amp;amp;bad=error/badfetch.html&amp;amp;entitytoprecno=4&amp;amp;entitycurrecno=4&quot;&gt;“Farming Country”&lt;/a&gt; by G. M. Schwartz from the University of Wisconsin Digital Collections.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/agnes/2017/04/23/agnes-state-college.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/agnes/2017/04/23/agnes-state-college.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Agnes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Meg and the Pure Americans</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When I first started researching the years that &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/meg&quot;&gt;Meg&lt;/a&gt; spent in rural western Maryland in the early 1920s, I knew next to nothing–only the short description written on her resume: “Part time worker, Frederick County, Md. School Health Inspection. Survey of farm tenancy for U. S. Dept. of Agriculture. Co-worker, Beulah Weldon Burhoe. Volunteer and experimental services. Expenses only.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was searching Meg’s name in historical newspapers when I came across a letter Beulah Weldon had written to her Barnard alumni magazine describing the “model farmstead” that she and Meg had started in Friends Creek, and this led me to more articles detailing their work at their settlement house, including a nearly full-page 1922 &lt;em&gt;Baltimore Sun&lt;/em&gt; article called “Maryland Has Forgotten Colonies of Anglo Saxons.” This article provided the most detailed accounting that I had seen thus far in my research, describing the history of the settlement and Meg and Beulah’s activities on Friends Creek–much of which I recounted in a &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/meg/2017/04/04/meg-pure-americans&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was reading this article, one line struck me as soon as I read it: “The Daughters of the American Revolution, who are greatly desirous of fostering patriotism and pure Americanism have contributed largely.” “Pure Americanism”? What did that mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read on and found the answer, in the words of my own great-great aunt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“‘My principal motive in leaving New York and coming here was to help the country children, the native Americana, to get a better share of what is due them,’ says Miss Newman. ‘In New York there are fine schools, which are almost swamped by the children of recent immigrants, eager to learn, but remote regions such as this are permitting the children, many of whom are direct descendants of Revolutionary war heroes, to grow up in ignorance.’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her comments, Meg voices anti-immigrant sentiments that were common in the early 1920s, and that led to laws restricting immigration, which placed quotas on the number of immigrants who could enter the U.S. from various countries. The laws favored Anglo-Saxon immigrants over those from Southern and Eastern Europe and Asia, in part to establish a specific American identity represented by “native-born” Americans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meg explained how her experience working with immigrants led her to want to help those who were “native-born.” Children in the cities, she thought, had opportunities to hear music, buy prepared food and ready-made dresses, and go to art galleries, whereas in rural areas ”the only music, if any, will be a fiddle playing ‘Sourwood Mountain,’ [and] the children have no music lessons. The girls will have to cook all their lives, but there is no one to show them the value of proper preparation of food. They will always have to make their own clothes, but there are no sewing lessons. The boys are taught no trades, and if they do not get disgusted and move away there is no hope for them to do anything else but day labor, with little profitable work at that.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meg also expressed contempt for some immigrants she knew who “had no spark of attachment whatever for this country and were simply using it for what they could get out of it, notwithstanding all that was being done for them.” Thinking of the children in rural areas, Meg said, she became “heartsick” and “determined to cast my lot with them and do what I could to remedy the injustice.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading these words was very upsetting to me. Meg is certainly expressing ideas that were shared by many at that time, including some settlement workers, who despite serving immigrants could not overcome their own prejudices. But where was the liberal, enlightened aunt I had heard about for so many years? Of all the aunts, I think of Meg as the most progressive. She marched for women’s suffrage, and after women got the vote, became an ardent Democrat who would get into fights with my much more conservative great-grandfather. I once heard a story that she took in an unwed pregnant woman and helped her get on her feet. She devoted her life to nursing others. When I first discovered that she had started her own rural settlement house, I had envisioned her as an idealistic, self-sacrificing revolutionary, but now that image has been complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially since I am descended from the very same people Meg considered to be taking what was not rightfully theirs, and not “pure Americans,” solely because of where they came from. My maternal great-grandparents immigrated from southern Italy and Sicily to the United States in the early 1900s, settling in New Haven, Connecticut. They worked in factories, learned English, and assimilated into American society. I have often felt a tension in my heritage; reading Meg’s words, I am more aware than ever of the distance that existed between my great-grandfather Samuel Newman, the president of a tool company in Waynesboro, Pennsylvania, and my great-grandfather Erasmo Brancato, a barber in New Haven, Connecticut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all make choices in our lives, and even when making the choice of devoting your life to service, you must make a choice of who you will serve. Which cause is the most worthy? Who needs your help the most? Meg saw a need in rural Maryland, and during the five years she served there, she undoubtedly did a great deal of good. When Meg first arrived at Friends Creek, only 12.5% of the children were at a normal weight; three years later, that number was at 80%. She organized visits from doctors at the school and transportation to the local hospital and to dentists for children who needed it. She and Beulah also expanded their settlement family, taking in local children who needed their help. Are these achievements tarnished in some way by the reasons Meg pursued them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I struggle with how to reconcile Meg’s good works with her prejudiced views. I admire her for her dedication to the people of Friends Creek, and for her courage in living an unconventional life that was different from the standard formula set for women. But I am also disappointed in her inability to surpass the dominant thinking of her age. Ultimately, I am understanding that yes, in many ways, Meg was a woman who was &lt;em&gt;ahead&lt;/em&gt; of her time, but she was also very much &lt;em&gt;of&lt;/em&gt; her time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;https://calisphere.org/item/ark:/13030/ft5r29p0d6/&quot;&gt;“Immigrants”&lt;/a&gt; by Johan Hagemeyer. From the Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Apr 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/meg/2017/04/04/meg-pure-americans.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/meg/2017/04/04/meg-pure-americans.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Meg</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Meg and Experimental Services</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 2, 1919, a rural schoolhouse opened its doors. The Friends’ Creek School, way up in the mountains of Western Maryland, had been closed for two years–teachers were hard to come by, especially for remote spots such as Friends’ Creek–but now it was the site of an experiment in settlement living, undertaken by two enterprising women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beulah Weldon, a twenty-six-year-old only a few years out of Barnard College, stood at the front of the class. With her was &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/meg&quot;&gt;Meg&lt;/a&gt;, who would use her nursing skills to improve the health and wellbeing of Beulah’s students, as well as that of the local community. Beulah and Meg’s venture was part of the settlement house movement; fueled mainly by young people seeking an outlet for putting into practice their progressive ideals, settlement houses and schools were established in many urban neighborhoods and isolated rural communities in the early 1900s. (Meg’s sister &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve&quot;&gt;Eve&lt;/a&gt; was &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve/2016/06/22/eve-ky-mts&quot;&gt;active in rural settlements in Kentucky&lt;/a&gt;.) These reform institutions provided education, health care, and other social services to their communities, grounding themselves in the idea that to understand and help others, one had to “settle” among them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before their move to the western Maryland mountains, Meg and Beulah had been active in settlement work in a much different community–New York City. They had met at the Henry Street Settlement House, a well-known institution founded by Lillian Wald in 1893. After she graduated from Barnard College in 1915, Beulah started working for the Committee for Vocational Schools at Henry Street. Meg started at Henry Street a few years before, in 1912, working as a staff nurse with Henry Street’s Visiting Nurse Service before becoming nurse-in-charge at the settlement’s convalescent and vacation homes in Montclair, New Jersey, and Grand View, New York. In 1919, the two decided to leave Henry Street and take their settlement mission to tiny, isolated Friends’ Creek, Maryland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Frederick (Maryland) &lt;em&gt;Daily News&lt;/em&gt; described Meg and Beulah’s “unique living arrangements,” which the newspaper described as ”like stories one reads of isolated western communities in pioneer days”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A small shack has been fitted up, as convenient to the school house as possible, and here Miss Weldon and Miss Newman will make their home. “Convenient to the school house” is a misleading phrase, however, as the shack is at least 3 or 4 miles distant, and teacher and nurse will have to drive to school every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(“School Open First Time in Two Years.” &lt;em&gt;The Daily News&lt;/em&gt; (Frederick, Maryland), 27 August 1919, p. 4.) The house came with 53 acres of land, as well as a pig pen, and over the next few years, they continued to make improvements, acquiring cows, a horse, chickens, and a flock of sheep, and adding a screened-in porch (a rarity in that area, the newspaper account claimed).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the vein of most rural settlement houses, Beulah and Meg set out to provide education, health care, and general services to the local community. After they had been at Friends’ Creek for a year, Beulah wrote a letter to her alumni journal, &lt;em&gt;The Barnard Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, sharing the progress that they had made: “I have taught the district school during the winter and Miss Newman has given health lessons, taught sewing, knitting and handwork, acted as school attendance officer and school nurse, and has made nursing visits when necessary,” Beulah wrote. “We succeeded in getting an appropriation from the Frederick County School Board to cover part of her salary. We have opened our home, which is a dilapidated little mountain house, as a recreation room. We are aiming to have a model farmstead and to influence our neighborhood through informal contacts made in our daily living.” (“Letters.” &lt;em&gt;The Barnard Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, 30 April 1920, p. 1.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea Beulah expressed of influencing their local community through “informal contacts made in our daily living” gets at the heart of the settlement movement and reflects a sentiment expressed by settlement pioneer Jane Addams, the founder of Chicago’s Hull House. Settlement residents, Addams wrote in her essay “The Subjective Necessity for Social Settlements,” “must be content to live quietly side by side with their neighbors until they grow into a sense of relationship and mutual interests.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meg and Beulah appear to have cultivated those relationships Addams noted in her essay. The “Friends’ Creek settlement,” as it was known, attracted support from the State Federation of Women’s Clubs, Rotary Club, and Daughters of the American Revolution. I also found mention of Beulah making several speeches on behalf of their work, bringing to mind the advocacy and fundraising that Eve did for the Hindman and Pine Mountain Settlement Schools, and the question, did Meg ever call upon her sister for support with her own settlement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One sister, at least, but not the one you’d expect. According to the &lt;em&gt;Baltimore Sun&lt;/em&gt;, in the summer of 1922, Meg’s sister Agnes, and her husband, Milton Lightwood, planned to join the Friends’ Creek settlement. Milton was going to be spending the summer “trying to instill into the natives a knowledge of better methods of farming. Part of his program is the establishment of a model hennery at the settlement. Even if the Misses Weldon and Newman had the technical training and the physical strength, they could do no good in agricultural instruction, for the men of the community would scorn to learn such things from a woman.” (“Maryland Has Forgotten Colonies of Anglo Saxons.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The model hennery and agricultural instruction are examples of the kind of experimentation that happened at Friends’ Creek, although the entire settlement was truly an experiment–Meg even described these years of work experience on her resume as “experimental services.” But experimentation was at the heart of the settlement movement. Jane Addams described the settlement as “an experimental effort to aid in the solution of the social and industrial problems which are engendered by the modern conditions of life in a great city.” The settlement, she said, must be flexible, quick to adapt, and ready to “change its methods as its environment may demand. It must be open to conviction, and have a deep and abiding sense of tolerance. It must be hospitable and ready for experiment.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading about the work that Meg and Beulah achieved at Friends’ Creek, as well as the idea of a settlement as a sort of “incubator” for new ideas, I am struck by the ingenuity and resiliency displayed by settlement workers, who were constantly observing new problems and trying out new ways to fix them. To take on this work, to move to an isolated community and live in a small, dilapidated shack, to dedicate their lives to improving the lives of others, required strength of purpose on the part of Meg and Beulah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what was this purpose? Why did they choose to devote themselves to “experimental services”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is complicated, and in many ways, a little painful for me. Meg and Beulah were certainly moved by the real need in the rural Maryland community, but their move to Maryland was also a rejection of the community that they were serving in New York City. The “deep and abiding sense of tolerance” Jane Addams valued in settlements? They didn’t have that. When this story continues, I’ll share what led Meg and Beulah to leave Henry Street, and how my perception of Meg, her life and work, is changing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Image: &lt;a href=&quot;http://collections.lib.uwm.edu/cdm/ref/collection/agsnorth/id/12346&quot;&gt;“United States, view of farm field in Flintstone, Maryland”&lt;/a&gt; by Robert S. Platt. From the American Geographical Society Library, University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/meg/2017/03/21/meg-experimental-services.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/meg/2017/03/21/meg-experimental-services.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Meg</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Who Was Alan Gilmour?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest mysteries I have uncovered in my research lies in a 1925 passenger list. On January 7, 1925, a ship called the S.S. Venezuela sailed from Corinto, Nicaragua, on its way to Los Angeles, California. On board appeared to be &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve&quot;&gt;Eve&lt;/a&gt;’s husband, Alan Gilmour. All of the details matched up, I noted: Family name: Gilmour. Given name: Alan P. Age: 54. Sex: M. Married or single: M[arried]. Date and place of birth: July 1st, 1870 - Henderson, Ky. But the next column held something surprising: a handwritten note that said: “Died in transit (suicide).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reread the note several times. Could I have misread the handwriting? Was this the correct person? I checked the personal details, then verified the date of his death–January 14, 1925–which matched with this record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard the unusual circumstances of Eve’s husband’s death–in fact I had heard very little about her husband at all. Alan Gilmour was only a minor character in my story of Aunt Eve’s life, noteworthy only for their &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve/2016/10/10/eve-last-year-kentucky&quot;&gt;Lincoln-inspired meeting at the Pine Mountain Settlement School&lt;/a&gt;. Their brief eight years of marriage were one of the least remarkable things that could be listed in Eve’s biography–which also includes a degree from Columbia, a lengthy career in social work, and a stint in North Africa with the Red Cross during World War II.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while my feminist soul cringes at the idea of defining women by the men in their lives, I do believe that the partners we choose to spend our days with are a reflection of our values and goals, even if for just a period in our lives. I decided to find out as much as I could about Alan Gilmour, in the hopes that understanding Eve’s choice of a life partner would tell me even more about her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://cdn.knightlab.com/libs/timeline3/latest/embed/index.html?source=1BCZUdgxVMlKjiZIhZ4cU1tfFBigph-gE6WuJzyDqwAE&amp;amp;font=Default&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;initial_zoom=2&amp;amp;height=650&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;allowfullscreen&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike Eve, Alan was born into a wealthy, aristocratic family; his father, Allan Gilmour, was a Scottish tobacco merchant, and his mother, Virginia Pegram, a Kentucky native whose mother was from the French West Indies. Although Alan was born in Kentucky, most of his childhood appears to have been spent in the seaside resort town of Helensburgh, Scotland, before he returned to the U.S. to study law. His privileged background was very different from what Eve experienced as a child; her father Jacob was a miller who was constantly moving the family from place to place and also, according to family stories, even left his wife and children behind in Pennsylvania to seek his fortune out west.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The constant impulse to seek out the next best thing is something Alan shared with his father-in-law. Although he mainly worked as a lawyer in Lexington, over the course of fifteen years, he moved four times–from Lexington to Alaska, to Detroit, back to Lexington, and finally to Los Angeles, California. He also dabbled in various careers, including automobile sales, local government, citrus farming, and real estate. I wonder how Eve viewed Alan’s inability to settle in one place–she certainly did not make a habit of doing so during her life, either. Later, as a social worker, she traveled around the country; her resume includes stints as a probation officer in New Mexico; with the Works Progress Administration in Oklahoma and Mississippi; as executive director of the Volunteer Placement Bureau in Pasadena, California; and as a social worker for city relief in Chicago. Perhaps their shared desire to seek out new opportunities and experiences was part of what drew them together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eve and her husband also shared a fearlessness and singlemindedness of purpose–think of a young Eve &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve/2016/09/06/eve-pine-mt&quot;&gt;marching into congressmen’s offices in Washington, D.C.&lt;/a&gt;, to rally support for the Pine Mountain Settlement School. As a young man, Alan showed his daring and impetuous nature, when, on Christmas night 1897, he ran off to offer his legal services to Cubans fighting the Cuban War of Independence (later the Spanish American War). The &lt;em&gt;Detroit Free Press&lt;/em&gt; reported that Alan left his boarding house, “stating that he should not return and, after a hasty visit to his cousin, W. P. Hamilton, of 56 Davenport street, left for the east.” In subsequent letters to his cousin and the law firm where he was employed, Alan announced his intention “to offer his personal services to the Cuban patriots. Mr. Gilmour was a member of the Naval Reserves,” the newspaper report recounted, “and was known as plucky and daring.” (“For Cuba Libre.” &lt;em&gt;The Detroit Free Press&lt;/em&gt;, 1 January 1897, p. 10)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:0px&quot; src=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=rIdz2V9UB10C&amp;amp;dq=alan%20pegram%20gilmour%20Year%20Book%20of%20the%20Society%2C%20Sons%20of%20the%20Revolution&amp;amp;pg=PT5&amp;amp;output=embed&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;500&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Portrait of Alan P. Gilmour from the Year Book of the Society, Sons of the Revolution, in the Commonwealth of Kentucky, 1894-1913, and Catalogue of Military Land Warrants Granted by the Commonwealth of Virginia to Soldiers and Sailors of the Revolution, edited by Samuel M. Wilson, Society, Sons of the Revolution, 1913.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout his life, Alan was not afraid to speak out or offend others, as documented in his many letters to the editor published in newspapers and periodicals from around the country. He called out the &lt;em&gt;Kentucky Evening Gazette&lt;/em&gt; for what he saw as their attempt to “make political capital” out of election day violence, praised the &lt;em&gt;Washington Post&lt;/em&gt; for its anti-British stance in 1915, opposed Woodrow Wilson and the League of Nations, and, in a memorable letter from 1901, came out against the United States’ support of the British during the Second Boer War. “It makes an American blush,” Alan wrote, “to think how his country is daily assisting the British in crushing out two little republics, battling for their independence, as we did over 100 years ago.” He went on to say that in 1900, he met the then-president of South Africa, Paul Kruger, in Holland, as well as the assistant secretary of state for foreign affairs of the Transvaal republic, who told him that the British army in South Africa would have been helpless without American supplies of fresh horses and mules. He urged the Detroit Transvaal League to start a movement or petition to stop the shipment of horses from the U.S., saying, “Surely the few paltry millions we make by the sale of such horses can not compensate us for the loss of our self-respect and national honor? And, as a nation, can we persist in such work–aiding and abetting farm burning, banishment, concentration camps and all–and retain our honor and self-respect? I think not.” (“From Free Press Readers.” &lt;em&gt;Detroit Free Press&lt;/em&gt;, 24 December 1901, p. 4.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan’s penchant for writing also found a more literary mode of expression–poetry. Periodicals and newspapers from the early 1900s are peppered with his poems, and he was one of the original stockholders in the &lt;em&gt;Kentucky Magazine&lt;/em&gt;, a publication, as you may guess, focused on Kentucky. Although mostly unremarkable, his poetry has patriotic, nationalistic themes, focusing on elements of Kentucky history, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=m8YWAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;dq=%22alan%20p%20gilmour%22&amp;amp;pg=PA360#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22alan%20p%20gilmour%22&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;“The Naming of Lexington,”&lt;/a&gt; or his adopted home state of California, as in “Van Nuys, California.” Alan also expressed his political opinions through poetry; in 1919, his poem “Good Enough for Me” declared his opposition to what he termed the “hypocritical League of (Imperialistic) Nations.” “The good old Declaration / Is good enough for me,” he stated. As is “the good old Constitution … fashioned / As a guard for Liberty” and “the good old Monroe Doctrine.” (Gilmour, Alan Pegram. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=UloxAQAAMAAJ&amp;amp;dq=%22alan%20pegram%20gilmour%22&amp;amp;pg=RA1-PA57#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22alan%20pegram%20gilmour%22&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;“Good Enough.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Harvey’s Weekly&lt;/em&gt;, 22 November 1919, p. 16.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe style=&quot;border: 0px;&quot; src=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=UloxAQAAMAAJ&amp;amp;dq=%22alan%20pegram%20gilmour%22&amp;amp;pg=RA1-PA74&amp;amp;output=embed&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; height=&quot;1000&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Alan’s more original creations came when he delivered a legal motion in the form of a poem. The poem talked about being excused from his wanderings from Lexington (he had just been in Alaska and Detroit for a number of years) and wanting to resume his work in the Lexington courts. “So with your kind permission, all / Once more I’ll try my fate, / In these legal halls of fair renown / Of Lexington, the Great!” According to Louisville’s &lt;em&gt;Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt;, “Judge Kerr smilingly remarked that the motion was granted.” (“Legal Motion in Rhyme.” &lt;em&gt;The Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt; [Louisville, KY], 1 December 1912, p. 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture of Alan as a spirited, opinionated, aspiring creative partner for Eve is ultimately clouded by the mystery that surrounds his death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are hints that Alan was developing an interest in Latin America in the years before his death. In 1921, he traveled to Mexico on a trip sponsored by the Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce, as part of a group that included “some of the most prominent business men of southern California, and every industry of that district is represented in the party.” (“Los Angeles Men Here Tomorrow on Mexico Trip.” &lt;em&gt;Arizona Republic&lt;/em&gt;, 7 February 1921, p. 12.) In 1923, he hosted two men with ties to Latin America, one the former head of the Latin American Trade Bureau who was developing a steamship line between Los Angeles and the west coast of Mexico, and the other the consul in Los Angeles representing Colombia. (“Noted Men Visitors at Gilmour Home.” &lt;em&gt;The Van Nuys News&lt;/em&gt; [Van Nuys, CA], 28 August 1923, p. 3.) These connections, when combined with Alan’s demonstrated interest in seeking out new opportunities, might suggest that he was pursuing economic interests in Latin America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan’s writings also show a lifelong engagement with the United States’ international activities, expressing his criticism of U.S. involvement in the Second Boer War and President Woodrow Wilson’s League of Nations. Could his political opinions on the U.S.’s interventions in Latin America have led him to Nicaragua in 1925? The United States had maintained a military presence in Nicaragua, dating from 1912, but in the same month that Alan sailed from the country, the U.S. announced that it would end its 13-year military presence there. Alan’s keen interest in foreign affairs may explain in part what led him to Nicaragua, but the mystery of his fatal voyage home remains and will likely never be fully resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Alan’s death, Eve found herself, at the age of 37, a widow. When she married Alan, Eve was a spirited, independent young woman, who had been seeking her own path in the world. With Alan, she had embarked on a life that was undoubtedly exciting, but at times, precarious and unstable. Yet neither this marriage, nor the manner of how it ended, defined her life. The same year that she was widowed, Eve moved back across the country to attend the New York School of Social Work, starting a new life defined in large part by her pioneering career.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/eve/2017/02/06/who-was-alan-gilmour.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/eve/2017/02/06/who-was-alan-gilmour.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Eve</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mary and the Riverside Library Service School</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1908, Joseph F. Daniels, librarian at the State Agricultural College Library in Fort Collins, Colorado, wrote an &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=AKlJAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;lpg=PA173&amp;amp;dq=people%3A%20a%20modern%20emphasis%20in%20library%20training&amp;amp;pg=PA173#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;em&gt;Library Journal&lt;/em&gt;. In it, he set out his vision for the training of librarians, stating:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is charged that an important aspect of training receives little attention, because the schools begin and end their courses of instruction with the book and its house (the “bookery,” as Mr. Hopkins calls it). And, while we cannot deny that books are fundamental in the idea of a library, we know that People are fundamental in the idea of service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniels criticized traditional library schools for what he saw as an overemphasis on theory, to the neglect of preparation for library work as a service to people. Library school students were trained to be “book servants,” receiving “technical training and efficiency,” which he deemed less important than “the development of the man or the woman who is to deal with the library and its People” (175-176).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, Daniels would put his philosophy toward library science education into action, starting a training school for librarians at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.riversideca.gov/library/about_history.asp&quot;&gt;Riverside Public Library&lt;/a&gt;: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://riversideca.gov/library/history_aids_libraryschool.asp&quot;&gt;Riverside Library Service School&lt;/a&gt;, its name reflecting its commitment to training librarians for service to the people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was at this unorthodox–often controversial–library school that &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/mary&quot;&gt;Mary Ellen Newman&lt;/a&gt; received her training as a librarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;§&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a newly minted librarian myself, I have a particular connection to Mary’s story. Three years ago, I was thinking seriously about a career change and settled upon librarianship. That decision was one that has changed my life and leads me to wonder why Mary made the same choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears at least that she had an early interest in books–one of the main reasons that drew (and continues to draw) people to the library profession. In 1954, she wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/25694134?seq=1#page_scan_tab_contents&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; to the &lt;em&gt;American Library Association Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;. “Long, long ago before we even had a public library in my home town of Waynesboro, Pennsylvania,” she wrote, “I belonged to a group of persons who met every fortnight to read and discuss books of great writers, devoting a winter to one author. Out of this developed ‘the Fortnightly Club’ which is still functioning in that town” (7). (see Note 1 below)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary’s membership in the Fortnightly Club hints at a connection to books and reading that may have led her into librarianship, but it does not explain why, by 1930, she had moved across the country to Riverside, California, where she received her degree in library work from the Riverside Library Service School.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary’s decision to move to the west coast is even more puzzling because at the time, most of the prominent library schools were on the east coast. In fact, Joseph Daniels founded the Riverside Library Service School in part to provide another opportunity for &lt;em&gt;west&lt;/em&gt; coasters to get library training without having to move to the &lt;em&gt;east&lt;/em&gt; coast. “It has annoyed me a long time to see our young people go east for training when it seemed unnecessary and expensive,” he explained in a letter to California State Librarian James Gillis. “They may get something good for them in and out of school in the east, but I am afraid that they get some things that are not always good for library progress” (qtd. in Hansen 977).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Mary’s east coast roots did not make her a likely Riverside student, in another respect, she was exactly the student that Daniels had envisioned when the school opened its doors in 1912. The first course offered at Riverside was a “short course,” aimed at those already working in libraries and/or those who had no formal education. Mary, though she had completed high school, had never gone to college, which was a requirement of many library schools at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniels did not want to discriminate against those students without formal higher education, for practical reasons. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=3LQUAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA19&amp;amp;dq=what+i+believe+about+library+schools+daniels&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwifp-LL5qvQAhXL64MKHXjKBYcQ6AEIOjAD#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=what%20i%20believe%20about%20library%20schools%20daniels&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;He wrote in &lt;em&gt;Public Libraries&lt;/em&gt; in 1913&lt;/a&gt; that the opportunities were far different for prospective librarians without formal education. “I believe that there should be a chance for any physically fit candidate, without age limit or ‘educational’ test who desires a chance,” he wrote, but only those with at least two years of college could expect to make a larger income. Because there were more libraries that paid “little reward,” he went on, “it is quite necessary in order to help all, that schooling be offered to the lesser librarians and to those of little reward” (19). The Riverside Library Service School’s commitment to providing educational opportunities to all candidates for library work set it apart from many other library schools at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniels’s school was also renowned–or perhaps notorious–for his unorthodox approach to library school curriculum. Namely, that there was none. In his &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=3LQUAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA19&amp;amp;dq=what+i+believe+about+library+schools+daniels&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwifp-LL5qvQAhXL64MKHXjKBYcQ6AEIOjAD#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=what%20i%20believe%20about%20library%20schools%20daniels&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;1913 &lt;em&gt;Public Libraries&lt;/em&gt; article&lt;/a&gt;, he outlined eleven points on “What I believe about library schools,” starting with “A library school should be conducted in a library, or adjacent to a library where people are served every day. People are the real consideration in a library.” He proposed dividing students into groups and having them rotate through each department in the library, preparing weekly reports “of all work and study, by station and by hours and by subject matter.” There would be “no assigned reading whatever: Let them listen at lectures or hunt for it,” and lectures should be given “only when needed and then by notable experts who have something more than knowledge of subject matter” (18-19).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that many of these ideas were put into practice at the Riverside Library Service School–to the consternation of many. Daniels’s approach to library education was criticized by many of his peers. One of the main sources of criticism was the Williamson Reports, reports evaluating library schools researched and written by Charles C. Williamson for the Carnegie Corporation. (see Note 2 below)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williamson did not think much of the Riverside Library Service School. “Of the school itself there was little tangible evidence,” he wrote. “What I saw going on was not much more than apprentice, or a ‘learn by doing’ method, but yet I left Riverside feeling that a year spent in that environment, no matter what the character of the formal instruction, would be excellent preparation for service in small town and rural libraries” (212). He rejected the idea that a public library could provide professional education for librarians and advised that the school at Riverside close and “all the library interests of the state” be focused on other schools in Los Angeles and Berkeley (212).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite these opinions on the quality of its program, the Riverside Library Service School would graduate over 1,000 students over the course of its 30 years’ existence, until it was indefinitely “suspended” in 1943 because of World War II. The school would never receive its accreditation, or official recognition as a library science degree program, from the American Library Association, the professional organization of American librarians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This didn’t hurt Mary’s chances at a library career, however. She went on from library school to work at the University of California at Riverside’s Citrus Experiment Station for thirty years. In this capacity, she contradicted both Daniels’s prediction of the career possibilities for “lesser librarians” and Williamson’s assessment that the Riverside Library Service School only prepared students for service in “small town and rural libraries.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;§&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways, Mary’s library science education, as so enthusiastically designed and espoused by Joseph Daniels, is the education that I didn’t find in library school itself, but the education that I think should be taught in library schools today. Over the two years I spent obtaining my degree, the people I learned the most from were not necessarily my professors, but my supervisors and colleagues who actively worked in libraries and were experts in their fields. My knowledge of the field came from reading blog posts, journal articles, and Twitter–readings I “hunted out,” rather than course lectures. And what truly prepared me to be a librarian was the immersive, hands-on experience of working in libraries and cultural heritage institutions–the practical training dismissed by Williamson as the “‘learn by doing’ method.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Librarianship has changed dramatically in the decades since Mary attended library school, but the ideas and values that formed the foundation of the Riverside Library Service School are still relevant in library science education today–a commitment to service and a focus on the community of people who come to libraries every day. Daniels’s call for a shift from training in “bookery” to training in service strongly echoes current re-imaginings of libraries from storage units for books to spaces for learning and community building. Seeing these connections across time imbues in my own career a sense of continuity and history and ties me ever more closely to Mary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note 1: Todd Dorsett’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=Ynx6jIfuU2YC&amp;amp;lpg=PA57&amp;amp;ots=M_0qvRfLGW&amp;amp;dq=fortnightly%20club%20waynesboro%20pennsylvania&amp;amp;pg=PA145#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=fortnightly%20club&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Waynesboro As We Knew It&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; describes the founding of the “Fortnightly Club,” attributing more than just reading to its activities. “A small group of local young ladies calling themselves the ‘Brownies’ took jaunts into the countryside, and camped at Mont Alto and the present Renfrew Museum and Park, which they christened ‘Camp Willow.’ They studied nature, wrote essays, and held entertainments” (145). One of the original “Brownies” was Mary R. Frantz, who was Mary’s first cousin, once removed. (Mary Frantz was Mary’s mother Emma Frantz’s first cousin–Mary Frantz’s father Benjamin Frantz and Emma’s father Samuel Frantz were brothers. Mary Frantz and Mary Newman were the same age, despite being in different generations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note 2: In 1919, the Carnegie Corporation enlisted Dr. Charles C. Williamson, Head of the Division of Economics and Sociology at the New York Public Library, to evaluate American library schools. As described in the foreword to the report, “all of the library schools in the United States were visited and carefully examined; the most expert opinions on the problem were analyzed and compared; and, finally, the use made of the product of these schools, together with the need and demand for more and better training, was subjected to as thorough a statistical study as the available material permitted” (v).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Works Referenced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniels, J.F. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=AKlJAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;lpg=PA173&amp;amp;dq=people%3A%20a%20modern%20emphasis%20in%20library%20training&amp;amp;pg=PA173#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;“People: A modern emphasis in library training.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Library Journal&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 33, 1908, pp. 173-176.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniels, J.F. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=3LQUAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA19&amp;amp;dq=what+i+believe+about+library+schools+daniels&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwifp-LL5qvQAhXL64MKHXjKBYcQ6AEIOjAD#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=what%20i%20believe%20about%20library%20schools%20daniels&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;“What I believe about library schools.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Public Libraries&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 23, 1913, pp. 18-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dorsett, Todd Andrew. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=Ynx6jIfuU2YC&amp;amp;lpg=PA57&amp;amp;ots=M_0qvRfLGW&amp;amp;dq=fortnightly%20club%20waynesboro%20pennsylvania&amp;amp;pg=PA145#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=fortnightly%20club&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Waynesboro As We Knew It&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt; Antietam Historical Association, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hansen, Debra Gold. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ideals.illinois.edu/bitstream/handle/2142/13710/Hansen_LT52_4.pdf&quot;&gt;“Personalizing Library Education, the California Connection: James Gillis, Everett Perry, and Joseph Daniels.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Library Trends&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 52, no. 4, 2004, pp. 963-987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newman, Mary Ellen. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jstor.org/stable/25694134&quot;&gt;“Book Club.”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;ALA Bulletin&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 48, no. 1, 1954, p. 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Riverside Library Service School.” &lt;em&gt;City of Riverside&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://riversideca.gov/library/history_aids_libraryschool.asp&quot;&gt;https://riversideca.gov/library/history_aids_libraryschool.asp&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 15 December 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Williamson, Charles C. “Training for Library Work: A Report Prepared for the Carnegie Corporation of New York.” &lt;em&gt;The Williamson Reports of 1921 and 1923.&lt;/em&gt; Scarecrow Press, 1971.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Header image: &lt;a href=&quot;http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/p15799coll65/id/8546&quot;&gt;“Riverside’s Public Library, ca. 1910.”&lt;/a&gt; from the University of Southern California Libraries and California Historical Society is released under a &lt;a href=&quot;http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 3.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/mary/2016/12/15/mary-riverside-library-service-school.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/mary/2016/12/15/mary-riverside-library-service-school.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Mary</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eve's Last Year in Kentucky</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In two previous posts, I’ve shared the story of how Eve became active in the rural settlement school movement in Kentucky, serving as field secretary for both the Hindman Settlement School and the Pine Mountain Settlement School. Now, I’ll be telling the end of that story, of how, after several years of raising money and support for the work of progressive-minded women in the Kentucky mountains, Eve left Pine Mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1915, the Pine Mountain Settlement School was well on its way to becoming a successful school and community center. New buildings were going up, more students were enrolling, and nursing and other community services were expanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eve’s role at the school was expanding as well. In February of 1915, she was elected to Pine Mountain’s General Advisory Board. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?attachment_id=12234&quot;&gt;Letter from Marguerite Butler, 2/24/1915&lt;/a&gt;) The board was a group of advisors, selected by the Executive Committee, which had “the power to direct and shape the policies of the school, to vote at all Board meetings, and to control the actions of the Board of Trustees.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?attachment_id=4873&quot;&gt;Board Report, January 3, 1914&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/letter.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Letter from Marguerite Butler, 1915&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Miss Newman was elected at the meeting a member of the board of the school.” “but_1915_01_026.jpg,” Marguerite Butler Letters, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Oct. 10.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1915, Eve also took up the cause to have a road built from Pine Mountain to the nearest railroad. A &lt;em&gt;Louisville Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt; article from April 20, 1915, related news of a meeting that took place between Eve and Road Commissioner R.C. Terrell “concerning State aid work in Harlan. The county failed to apply in time, and Miss Newman said she intends to urge the county officers to make their plans this year so as to take advantage of the State aid plan next year.” (“Harlan Woman Seeks State Aid for County,” &lt;em&gt;The Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt;, April 21, 1915) (N.B. The road over Pine Mountain was not actually completed until 1940, according to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?p=4736&quot;&gt;history of the “Laden Trail” published on the Pine Mountain Settlement School Collections website&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite Eve’s continued activities with Pine Mountain, by fall 1915, she was planning to leave the school, if only for a short time. In a letter dated early fall 1915, Marguerite Butler reported: “Miss Newman, the regular secretary, is leaving for a year’s study at Columbia.” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?attachment_id=12266&quot;&gt;Letter from Marguerite Butler, early fall 1915&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no mention of whether Eve intended to return to Pine Mountain after completing her studies, but, if so, her plans changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 31, 1915, Eve’s father, Jacob Newman, justice of the peace in Waynesboro, Pennsylvania, signed a marriage license application for Eve, then a 27-year-old student, and Alan Pegram Gilmour, a 45-year-old attorney from Lexington, Kentucky. They were married in Waynesboro on February 12, 1916.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always wondered how Eve met Alan Gilmour–an older man, established attorney, son of a wealthy Scottish tobacco merchant, captain in the Kentucky National Guard, and “prominent citizen”–according to the &lt;em&gt;Louisville Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt;. (&lt;em&gt;The Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt;, January 2, 1916). Some deep digging revealed that Alan practiced law in the same building as Charles Wilson, who sat on the Board of Trustees of the Pine Mountain Settlement School, but this was the only connection that I could find… until I stumbled upon a newspaper article that offered an answer to this mystery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Lincoln’s birthday anniversary on February 12 will be celebrated by Capt. Alan P. Gilmour, of this city, the well-known lecturer on ‘Abraham Lincoln,’ by his marriage on that day to Miss Eve Newman, the wedding to be held at the home of Miss Newman’s sister in Columbia, N.Y.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The marriage will be the direct result of a romance brought about through the subject of Lincoln. Last summer Miss Newman, whose home is in Waynesboro, Pa., was visiting Miss Katherine Pettet [sic] at the Pine Mountain School in Eastern Kentucky when Capt. Gilmour went over there to deliver his lecture on Abraham Lincoln at a Fourth of July celebration. He is an enthusiast on the subject and made the lecture so interesting and eloquent that Miss Newman, who was in the audience, became attracted by what he had to say, and, meeting later, Mr. Gilmour began to pay court and so is now preparing to carry out his plan of celebrating Lincoln’s birthday with this most important event of his life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(“Lincoln Lecture Won Her,” &lt;em&gt;The Courier Journal&lt;/em&gt;, January 31, 1916)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entertaining account of their courtship leaves me with so many unanswered questions: How often did Alan make the arduous trek over the mountain from Lexington to “pay court”? If Eve and Alan were engaged by the end of the year, when did Eve leave Pine Mountain? And how much of an “enthusiast” of Lincoln was Alan?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last question proved easiest to answer. Newspaper articles show that Alan Gilmour was indeed an enthusiast of Abraham Lincoln. At the Lexington Memorial Day services in 1913, he recited Lincoln’s Gettysburg Address. (&lt;em&gt;The Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt;, May 26, 1913) He also offered a prize of “$5 in gold” to the Lincoln Model School student who gave the “best rendition of Lincoln’s Gettysburg speech” and presented to the school “a large, elegantly framed facsimilie [sic] in blue print of the tablets placed in all our national cemeteries, upon which are engraved the immortal address.” (&lt;em&gt;The Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt;, October 10, 1913) A few years later, Alan would even publish an article on the “Patriotism of Lincoln” in &lt;em&gt;The Kentucky Magazine&lt;/em&gt;. (“The Kentucky Magazine for November,” &lt;em&gt;The Bourbon News&lt;/em&gt;, November 6, 1917)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of when Eve left her work at Pine Mountain is harder to figure out. In a letter dated Spring 1916, Marguerite Butler stated that Eve would be away until the end of April. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?attachment_id=12143&quot;&gt;Letter from Marguerite Butler, Spring 1916&lt;/a&gt;) By that time, however, Eve was married and living in Lexington, Kentucky, with Alan. She may have continued to serve on the board for some time after that, but her documented engagements all appear to have been in Lexington, such as when she was elected president of the Civil League for the year of 1917. (“Mrs. Gilmour President,” &lt;em&gt;The Courier-Journal&lt;/em&gt;, December 8, 1916) A few years after that, Eve and Alan had left Kentucky behind for the west coast, settling in southern California, where Eve would remain for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/eve-alan.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Eve Newman and Alan Gilmour&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although perhaps no fixed relationship existed between Eve and Pine Mountain in the years that followed her move to California, the influence of the school was long-lasting. Her career in social work, her devotion to improving the lives of children, her strength and determination–all can be traced back to her time in the Kentucky mountains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Header image: Top of Pine Mountain. “nace_1_010a.jpg,” Dorothy Nace Photograph Album I Part I, Photographs, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Oct. 10.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/eve/2016/10/10/eve-last-year-kentucky.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/eve/2016/10/10/eve-last-year-kentucky.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Eve</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Agnes and the School of Forestry</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Each Saturday in the early 1900s, the small town of Waynesboro, Pennsylvania, was greeted with an unusual sight: a group of young men, riding through town on their horses, on break from the Pennsylvania State Forest Academy in nearby Mont Alto. “The young girls would be sitting on their front porches, dressed in their best, and waiting for the foresters to arrive,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forrest_H._Duttlinger_Natural_Area&quot;&gt;Forrest H. Dutlinger&lt;/a&gt;, an Academy alumnus and Pennsylvania forester, later recalled. But, “nothing much happened when they did. The group chatted with girls they knew or rode aimlessly around town. Sometimes, as they were leaving, they would pull on the reins until their horses plunged and reared, fire their pistols into the air, yell, ‘Whoopee!’ and gallop off toward the academy.” (Thomas, p. 485)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/agnes&quot;&gt;Agnes&lt;/a&gt; sit on her East Third Street porch, watching the foresters-in-training ride through town? And was this weekly occurrence one of the reasons why, in 1916, at the age of 21, Agnes applied to attend the Forest Academy? Had she joined the Academy, she would have studied forestry and surveying; patrolled the state forests to prevent vandalism and fire, with a state-issued pistol at the ready; and worked in the woods, cutting fire lanes, raising seedlings, and taking inventory of the trees–all in preparation for a career in the State Department of Forestry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, Agnes was refused entrance to the Forest Academy, she later related in an interview with the &lt;em&gt;Waynesboro Record Herald&lt;/em&gt;, because she was a woman. (“Agnes Harbaugh… Spotlight on an Action Oriented Woman”) The article cites Agnes’ application to the school as an example of her early feminist leanings–well before the second wave of feminism in the mid-20th century. She did not allow gender expectations to limit her aspirations, even though forestry–despite its connection to the progressive conservation movement–was primarily a masculine profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forestry as a career emerged during the Progressive Era, as part of a growing conservation movement concerned with the destruction of finite natural resources. Theodore Roosevelt was a champion of conservationism; during his administration, he created the Forest Bureau (later the Forest Service) and established &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/thro/learn/historyculture/theodore-roosevelt-and-conservation.htm&quot;&gt;150 national forests&lt;/a&gt;. Conservationists like Roosevelt were not motivated solely by a desire to conserve the beauty of nature, but to protect and sustain future economic development, as the President stated in a 1901 message to Congress: “Forest protection is not an end of itself; it is a means to increase and sustain the resources of our country and the industries which depend upon them.” (McGerr, p. 166)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Pennsylvania, a movement to preserve the state’s forests was sparked, in part, through the efforts of women. “Impelled by the increasing destruction of the noble forests of Pennsylvania,” a group of women in Philadelphia were moved to “concerted action in the way of forest preservation and the replanting of waste lands, in order to supply the timber for the absolute needs of the near future.” (Shepper, p. 4) The women organized a public meeting, and their efforts led to the formation of the Pennsylvania Forestry Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the conservation movement took hold, and the state continued to purchase lands for forestry purposes, some expressed a need for “men” who were trained to care for the land. In 1901, Dr. Joseph T. Rothrock, the “father of Pennsylvania forestry,” outlined his plan for a school that would “guarantee to the State in the promptest and most certain manner, and without any pecuniary risk to the Commonwealth, a body of trained foresters who will be intimately acquainted not only with forestry principles, but with the ground upon which these principles are to be applied.” (Clepper, p. 13) The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penn_State_Mont_Alto#Pennsylvania_State_Forest_Academy&quot;&gt;Pennsylvania State Forest Academy&lt;/a&gt; was established in May 1903.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book &lt;a href=&quot;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015068568198;view=1up;seq=23&quot;&gt;Forestry Education in Pennsylvania&lt;/a&gt;, edited by Henry Clepper, an Academy alumnus, provides a detailed description of the early years of the school. The Academy was a three-year program; each student received a scholarship, and, starting with the class of 1909, had to serve three years in the state after completing the program. The year before Agnes applied, admission requirements changed. In addition to completing a rigorous entrance exam, the applicants had to complete six weeks of field training in the state forests. The program appears to have been quite competitive, admitting only small numbers of students in the early years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No sources that I have read document an official rule against women at the school. Clepper’s history does state that the class of 1925, which registered in September 1921, did include a woman, “the wife of a member of the class of 1922. Although she successfully completed the first year, she did not return. She was the first and last of the female students.” (Clepper, p. 22-23) Five years after Agnes’ application, a woman &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; allowed to attend the school–although the caveat that she was the spouse of another student points to the power of circumstance, rather than a more open admission policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men continued to dominate the forestry profession for decades. In 1969, the first woman received an M.S. in forest resources from Penn State, but it was not even until 1984 that a woman was hired by the Pennsylvania Bureau of Forestry. (Gerhold, p. 100)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agnes is known in our family as someone who was not afraid to break the rules, and her application to the Pennsylvania State Forest Academy is yet another example. With her application, she challenged the expectations of what a woman &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; do at that time. How she reacted after the rejection is also telling of her character; not allowing the decision to stifle her educational ambitions, the next year, she entered Penn State, where she studied horticulture and, after raising three children, embarked on a long and exciting career–even if it did not involve wielding pistols against vandals and battling forest fires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;§&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note&lt;/em&gt;: The &lt;em&gt;Waynesboro Record Herald&lt;/em&gt; interview states that Agnes was refused admission to “Penn State’s School of Forestry at Mont Alto.” In 1916, there were two Pennsylvania institutions for forestry education: the Pennsylvania State Forest Academy in Mont Alto and Penn State’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libraries.psu.edu/psul/digital/forestry.html&quot;&gt;Department of Forestry&lt;/a&gt; in State College. The two schools merged in 1929. Because the school referenced in the article was located in Mont Alto, which was near Waynesboro, my educated guess is that Agnes would have applied to the Forest Academy, rather than Penn State, and I have written this post under that assumption. The &lt;em&gt;Record Herald&lt;/em&gt; article, written decades later, names Penn State as the institution sponsoring this program, which was correct at the time the article appeared in print, but not at the time when Agnes applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Photo&lt;/em&gt;: The Pennsylvania State Forest Academy Class of 1908 in front of Wiestling Hall. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libraries.psu.edu/psul/digital/forestry.html&quot;&gt;Credit: Penn State&lt;/a&gt;. Licensed under a &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/2.0/&quot;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-No Derivatives 2.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;. No changes were made to this image. According to Penn State, when the photo was developed, a ghostly figure appeared in the background, observing the figures on horseback. Can you find it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Works Referenced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Agnes Harbaugh… Spotlight on an Action-Oriented Woman.” &lt;em&gt;Waynesboro Record Herald&lt;/em&gt;. 1975.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clepper, Henry Edward. &lt;a href=&quot;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015068568198;view=1up;seq=23&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Forestry Education in Pennsylvania&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. University Park (PA): Penn State-Mont Alto Forestry Alumni Association, 1957.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gerhold, Henry D. &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=Ys1muh3jqXsC&amp;amp;pg=PA270&amp;amp;lpg=PA270&amp;amp;dq=pennsylvania+state+forestry+department+female+students&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=5f-Q_RnnDJ&amp;amp;sig=gCWXVLBlTEKF8DTXvrJy-NAo5_c&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjl4JH73oPPAhUCPj4KHYDqC8YQ6AEIPzAG#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Century of Forest Resources Education at Penn State: Serving Our Forests, Waters, Wildlife, and Wood Industries&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. University Park (PA): Pennsylvania State University Press, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McGerr, Michael. &lt;em&gt;A Fierce Discontent: The Rise and Fall of the Progressive Movement in America, 1870-1920.&lt;/em&gt; New York: Free Press, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thomas, Elizabeth H. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imakenews.com/psaanews/e_article003238407.cfm?x=b11,0,w&quot;&gt;“Student Life at the Pennsylvania State Forest Academy, 1905-1910.”&lt;/a&gt; Kittochtinny History Society, n.d.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/agnes/2016/09/23/agnes-forestry.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/agnes/2016/09/23/agnes-forestry.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Agnes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Eve and the Pine Mountain Family</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When last we left &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve&quot;&gt;Eve&lt;/a&gt;, she was 25, living in rural Hindman, Kentucky, and &lt;a href=&quot;/newman-aunts/eve/2016/06/22/eve-ky-mts&quot;&gt;working as a secretary for the Hindman Settlement School&lt;/a&gt;, traveling around the country to gather support–and funds–for the school. Hindman had been founded at the turn of the 20th century by two women–May Stone and &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=424&quot;&gt;Katherine Pettit&lt;/a&gt;–who had first been enlisted by the Women’s Christian Temperance Union to organize summer camps for settlement work in the Kentucky mountains. They stayed on, starting a permanent settlement school, which, after a decade, had built an industrial education program, an agricultural experiment station, a farm and dairy, and a hospital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But around 1911, Pettit was ready to move on. When she had first started her settlement work in Kentucky, she had visited Pine Mountain, an area of Kentucky that was even more isolated than Hindman and not yet accessible by the railroad. This was an area with a definite need for education, health care, and community outreach, and there was strong local support for a settlement school. Pettit began to scout locations for her school and recruited Hindman’s principal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=1696&quot;&gt;Ethel De Long&lt;/a&gt;, to join her. But before Pettit would leave Hindman, she wanted to secure that school’s future by raising an endowment of $100,000, and Aunt Eve had a large part to play in this effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1911, Campbell Bascom Slemp, a Republican congressman from Virginia, wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?attachment_id=28467&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; to Katherine Pettit, describing a visit he had just had from Eve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;About a week ago a young lady blew into my office stating that she represented your institution at Hindman and seemed to be on the search for Mr. Mayo and also any other individuals who might be interested in her cause. It happened to be at the time that I was going to New York to see Mr. Mayo, and some other gentlemen on some very important business matters, and I suggested that Miss Newman go along with me to see Mr. Mayo and also Mrs. Mayo, who was in New York with her husband.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congressman Slemp picked up the story in New York, where he and Eve met with various wealthy donors, convincing them to donate money to the school. They “stayed right on the ‘job’ to use a term that Miss Newman tells me you like to use,” wrote Slemp, and finally, he shared, “Miss Newman secured for the endowment feature of your school $25,000 in preferred stock of the Elkhorn Fuel Co.” This gift would yield a net annual income of $1250 to the Hindman School. Slemp also wrote that he secured letters of introduction for Eve and himself to Andrew Carnegie and Mrs. Russell Sage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slemp closed his letter by sharing his reasons for being invested in these efforts, the third being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;the very pleasing and charming personality of your representative. Her devotion to the interest of the Hindman school[,] her naturally unaffected disposition as well as her personal attractions appealed to all of us very strongly and I really think this was one of the contributory causes of the enthusiasm all of us had while in New York. I mention all these things because I thought you would like to know all of the details connected with this last work and our mental impressions as we went along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This letter provides a fascinating description of the mechanics behind fundraising in the early 1900s–traveling from city to city, enlisting the support of persons in power, obtaining letters of introduction, and arranging meetings. Persistence and enthusiasm were weighed against an established social order, which required deliberate orchestrations and the cultivation of relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also love this letter for what it tells us about Eve. From the very opening of the letter, when Eve “blows in” to Congressman Slemp’s office, we are presented with a woman who is dedicated to her cause and will not take “no” for an answer. At the end of his letter, Slemp praises her “devotion,” her “unaffected disposition,” even her “personal attractions” (!), attributing much of their fundraising success to Eve herself. Though this account is hardly, it seems, impartial, it establishes an idea of Eve as a determined young woman, which we can explore further while surveying her time at the Pine Mountain Settlement School.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While fundraising efforts for both Hindman and Pine Mountain continued, Pettit and De Long were making arrangements for the site of their new school, on land donated by William Creech, a farmer, large landowner, and community leader, who greatly wanted a school on Pine Mountain. After some negotiations between Creech and the Kentweva Coal and Lumber Company, the two women finally had their land: over two hundred acres on the north slope of Pine Mountain, where two creeks joined to form Greasy Creek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pine Mountain Settlement School officially opened in the spring of 1913, with a borrowed house, a Masonic Lodge building, some tents–and big plans. Over the next few months, the small, determined group of women prepared their land for farming, ordered and transported a sawmill over the mountain, built foot logs over the creek, fenced in their land against wandering neighborhood hogs, petitioned the local Fiscal Court for the building of a road over the mountain, organized Saturday afternoon clubs and Sunday Schools for the nearby children, and put on a Fourth of July celebration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/wagons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wagons arriving at Pine Mountain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wagons arriving at Pine Mountain, May 12, 1913. “hook_album_2blk__019,” Mary Rockwell Hook Album II, Photographs, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 6.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They also planned for the expansion of the school, soliciting help from agricultural and engineering experts, who gave them advice on land use, buildings, and septic systems. Mary Rockwell Hook, a Kansas City architect, also volunteered her services. On her first visit to Pine Mountain, she later recalled in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=12743&quot;&gt;1920 speech&lt;/a&gt;, “We three tramped over their acres, studying the different streams for water supply, levels and sites for buildings and gradually laying out a comprehensive plan for the complete development of a school of industry for 150 children.” Hook’s eventual &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=12710&quot;&gt;Land Use Plan&lt;/a&gt; succinctly stated how the school’s layout reflected the values of the school: “The founders of Pine Mountain knew that the physical characteristics of the land and the building expressed the spiritual ideals of the school. Therefore they wanted to keep the native character of the landscape setting and took, through the course of years, unimaginable pains to preserve each detail that contributed to the picture of a characteristic mountain valley.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Eve was not part of the original “family” who moved in to the school in the spring of 1913, by 1914, she was established at Pine Mountain and serving as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=17947&quot;&gt;office and field secretary&lt;/a&gt;. Eve continued to travel on lecturing tours to raise money and support for the school. Catherine Rittenhouse, a summer worker in 1914, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=1729&quot;&gt;mentions one such trip&lt;/a&gt;, a two-week trip in July 1914, on which Eve and Ethel De Long hoped to raise $7,500.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pine Mountain was located in a rural, mountainous area of Kentucky, accessible only by foot or mule. For Eve, who had to travel often, this must have been difficult, as illustrated by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?attachment_id=4889&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; written by Ethel De Long, in which she provides detailed instructions about how their new housekeeper could get to Pine Mountain from New York, a journey that took the better part of two days, and involved taking three trains, followed by a six-mile trek on foot or horseback: “The easiest way of coming is by the Southern Express to Bristol, Tennssee [sic], which leaves New York about nine-thirty P. M. … She will reach Bristol the next after noon where she must buy another ticket for Pineville, Kentucky. … Reaching Pineville about eleven o’clock that night she can stay at the Pineville Hotel or the Continental … Her train for Dillon leaves the next morning at seven-thirty-three. At one stop, Harlan, she has forty minutes to get off the train while it goes about private business of its own, and she can get a certain sort of lunch at the Busy-Bee Restaurant. From Dillon the remaining six miles is either on horseback or afoot … She ought to reach the school by half past two.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/report.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ethel De Long's detailed instructions for traveling to Pine Mountain&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ethel De Long’s detailed instructions for traveling to Pine Mountain. “reports_board_1913_21_027,” 1913 Director’s Letters to Board of Trustees, Series 5: Administration - Board of Trustees Correspondence, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 5.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to her duties as secretary, Eve was very much a part of the “family” at Pine Mountain, responsible for caring for the children and assisting with activities and events at the school. She lived in “Old Log,” a renovated log cabin dating from the early 1800s, with Ethel De Long and the young boys who boarded at the school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/log.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Old Log&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Old Log. “II_5_old_log_office_201.jpg,”Old Log,” Series 10: Built Environment, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 5.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around June of 1914, they moved into the newly renovated house, and Ethel described the experience in a letter to her mother: “The house, you know, is the old-fashioned two pens and a passage—with wide front porch. … I must tell you more of this household. Me—the oldest and most responsible, Chester, aged 12 and his fascinating little brother aged 6…; Miss Newman in the other room and little Monroe, aged 9, with her.” (Letter from Ethel DeLong to her mother, June 5, 1914)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/monroe.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Monroe&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Monroe (right), Eve’s roommate in Old Log in 1915. “roe_025a-1024x1007,” Philip Roettinger Album - Part I, Photographs, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 6.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A November 1914 &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=16345&quot;&gt;letter&lt;/a&gt; to the Friends of Pine Mountain described Old Log, as it was when Eve lived there: “With its wide porch, fireplace, and charming low-ceiled rooms, it preserves the cheerful homeliness of pioneer days. … True to the spirit of the old days it is a hospitable house … In the morning it hums with sounds, while untrained little hands are learning how to make its beds ‘pretty’ and keep its floors clean. At night you hear astonishing things, as teeth are washed and feet are scrubbed for bed. ‘I aim to stay with ye till you run me off. You don’t reckon you’ll run me off till I’m twenty, do ye?’”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/bridge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Bridge over Greasy Creek&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Foot log over Greasy Creek. “pmss3182,” XII Helen de Long Photograph Album, Photographs, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 5.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to their work at the school, Eve and the other settlement workers often traveled into the local community. In September 1914, teacher Marguerite Butler &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=11320&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; that she was staying in the log cabin “taking care of Miss Newman’s boys for she has gone off in the mountains to spend the night.” That fall Eve, Marguerite, and summer worker Ethel McCullough also took a five-mile walk down Greasy Creek to a religious meeting. Because of the rain, the creeks were high, so they had what Marguerite &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=11320&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; as “many exciting experiences trying to cross.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marguerite also &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=11320&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; a trip on mules that she took with Eve and teacher Margaret Watts. “It was a glorious and a glorious country through which we went. Honestly, our trail beat the Grand Canyon one in places in roughness. Three times the trail simply ended, but spying it again in the distance we took courage to go on. In the whole day we met about five people and only passed about four houses. You never saw such a wilderness.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/horses.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Riders on horseback&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“cale_1914_004_img,” 1914 Calendar, Series 24: PMSS Publications (Published by the School), Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 6.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 21, 1914, Eve left with Katherine Pettit and Ethel De Long on a twenty-mile walking trip down Greasy Creek. Marguerite &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=11320&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; that “they were pictures in their khaki skirts and middies, with their clothes slung over their back in some fetching pack.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the spare and often difficult living conditions, the young women who worked at Pine Mountain became friends and formed a family at the school. Catherine Rittenhouse &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=1729&quot;&gt;related&lt;/a&gt; having tea and talking with Eve about how people live in the mountains. “E. said, humorously, that living at home is not one half as complicated as here, for there, when you want anything, all you have to do is to ring a bell.” In September 1914, Eve joined Marguerite and architect Mary Rockwell in a tent to make room for the school’s guests. “Last night Miss Newman stayed with us too,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=11320&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; Marguerite, “so she and I spent the night in one single bed which was on the very edge of the tent floor over quite a little precipice. Once she nearly went out of bed and you ought to have heard the scream.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/newman-aunts/assets/images/workers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Marguerite Butler and two other workers&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Marguerite Butler (left) and two other workers. “X_100_workers_2537_mod-788x1024,” Workers at Pine Mountain Settlement School - II, Photographs - BX100, PIne Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 6.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marguerite also &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?attachment_id=13795&quot;&gt;described&lt;/a&gt; a night when everyone gathered at Ethel and Eve’s log house for stories, singing, and playing games. “After the little boys went to bed Miss De Long, Miss Newman, Peg, Ethel [McCullough], the two new workers and I sat around talking and feasting on cider, just made that day, nuts, raisins and cakes. We talked about plans for the school, what we would [sic] next year and all until it got very exciting.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/?page_id=11320&quot;&gt;Another night&lt;/a&gt;, Marguerite, housekeeper Ruth Gaines, teacher Margaret Rothery, Peggy, and Eve “had a grand supper cooking the steak [sent by Marguerite’s father] before the living room fire. We couldn’t bear the thought of frying it so broiled on a home-made arrangement right on top of the hot coals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These stories depict both the hard work and excitement that filled the early days of the Pine Mountain Settlement School. The women who journeyed over the mountain to join in the work of the school were devoted to their cause and courageous in their efforts to make a difference in the lives of the “mountain people.” Knowing that Eve was a part of the Pine Mountain community makes me wonder how this experience affected the choices that she made later on in her life; her decision to become a social worker, to work with children, must have been motivated in part by her time at Hindman and Pine Mountain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eve’s story at the Pine Mountain Settlement School is not finished, however. The school was responsible for setting her on her next adventure, which I’ll share in my next post about Eve in the Kentucky mountains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: My research into the Pine Mountain Settlement School would not have been possible without the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pinemountainsettlement.net/&quot;&gt;Pine Mountain Settlement School Collections&lt;/a&gt;, a project that is digitizing and making publicly available the school’s archives, from 1913 to the present day. I hope someday to visit the archives in person, but in the meantime, I am grateful to the hard work of all involved in this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Header image: “hook_album_2blk__034-1024x537,” Mary Rockwell Hook Album II, Photographs, Pine Mountain Settlement School, Pine Mountain, KY. 2016 Sept. 6.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 Sep 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/eve/2016/09/06/eve-pine-mt.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/newman-aunts/eve/2016/09/06/eve-pine-mt.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>Eve</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
